Finding Aid for Harry Benford papers, 1937-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Harry Benford papers
1937-2014
Benford, Harry.
85739 Aa 2
Harry B. Benford was professor and chair of the department of naval architecture and marine engineering at the University of Michigan. The Benford collection includes professional correspondence and topical files relating to his work, teaching, and research.
14.2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection has been donated in multiple accessions from 1955 to 2014 by Harry B. Benford (Donor No. 3123 )
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open except for departmental reviews memos (located in security vault) which require permission of the donor.
Harry B. Benford was born on August 7, 1917 in Schenectady, New York. After graduating from the University of Michigan in 1940, he worked at Newport News Shipbuilding Company for eight years before coming to the University of Michigan to teach in the Department of Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering. Professor Benford was chair of the department from 1967 to 1972. In addition, he also served as executive director of the National Academy of Sciences/National Research Council maritime research advisory committee from 1959 to 1960.
The Harry B. Benford Papers consists of correspondence and topical files relating to his work, teaching, and research.
Subjects:
Australia.; Benford, Harry.; Japan.; Kummerman, Henri, 1908-; National Research Council (U.S.). Maritime Transportation Research Board.; Naval architecture.; South America.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Students--Political activity.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1971-1980.; Demonstrations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers (U.S.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (8.2 linear feet, 1959-2014) consists of Benford's professional and personal correspondence from 1961 to 2014. Certain files in this series contain notes written by Benford giving background information on the correspondent or explaining the context of the folder's content.
  - 1959-1963 (Box 1)
  - 1967 (Box 1)
  - 1968 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1969 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1969 (Box 1)
  - July-September 1969 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1969 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1970 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1970 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972 (Box 1)
  - January-February 1973 (Box 1)
  - March 1973 (Box 1)
  - April-December 1973 (Box 1)
  - January-August 1974 (Box 1)
  - September-October 1974 (Box 1)
  - September-October 1974 (Box 1)
  - November-December 1974 (Box 1)
  - January-February 1975 (Box 1)
  - March-April 1975 (Box 1)
  - May-June 1975 (Box 1)
  - July-August 1975 (Box 1)
  - September-October 1975 (Box 1)
  - November-December 1975 (Box 1)
  - January 1976 (Box 1)
  - February-March 1976 (Box 1)
  - April-May 1976 (Box 1)
  - June-December 1976 (Box 1)
  - January-February 1977 (Box 1)
  - March 1977 (Box 1)
  - April-August 1977 (Box 1)
  - September-December 1977 (Box 1)
  - 1978 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1979 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1979 (Box 1)
  - July-September 1979 (Box 2)
  - October-December 1979 (Box 2)
  - January-March 1980 (Box 2)
  - April-July 1980 (Box 2)
  - August-December 1980 (Box 2)
  - 1981 (Box 2)
  - 1982, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1983 (Box 2)
  - 1983 (Box 2)
    (incoming)
  - 1983 (Box 2)
    (outgoing)
  - 1984 (Box 2)
  - 1984 (Box 2)
  - 1985, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1985 (Box 2)
  - 1986 (Box 2)
  - 1986 (Box 2)
  - 1986-1988, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1987 (Box 2)
  - 1987 (Box 2)
  - 1989, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1990 (Box 3)
  - 1991 (Box 3)
  - 1992 (Box 3)
  - 1993, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - December 1993-June 1994 (Box 3)
  - July 1994-March 1995 (Box 3)
  - April 1995-January 1996, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1996 (Box 4)
  - January-June 1996 (Box 4)
  - September 1996-September 1997 (Box 4)
  - November 1996-May 1997 (Box 4)
  - November 1996-March 2006 (Box 4)
  - June-December 1997 (Box 4)
  - December 1997-June 1998 (Box 4)
  - December 1997-January 1999, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - February-March 1999 (Box 4)
  - April-August 1999 (Box 4)
  - September-December 1999 (Box 4)
  - January-June 2000 (Box 4)
  - June 2000-November 2000 (Box 5)
  - December 2000-February 2001 (Box 5)
  - March 2001-August 2002 (Box 5)
  - September 2001-November 2001 (Box 5)
  - December 2001-March 2002 (Box 5)
  - 2001-2003 (Box 5)
  - April 2002-June 2002 (Box 5)
  - April 2002-July 2002 (Box 5)
  - August 2002-September 2002 (Box 5)
  - October-December 2002 (Box 5)
  - 2003, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - 2003, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - December 2003-December 2005 (Box 6)
  - December 2003-April 2005 (Box 6)
  - 2004 (Box 6)
  - January-April 2004, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - March 2005-January 2006, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - August-November 2006 (Box 6)
  - November 2006-December 2006 (Box 6)
  - 2007 (Box 6)
  - 1988-2010, 2 folders (Box 13)
    (correspondence with Eileen Zimmie Ebin)
  - April-May 2007 (Box 13)
  - May-July 2007 (Box 13)
  - August-October 2007 (Box 13)
  - September-November 2007 (Box 13)
  - November-December 2007 (Box 13)
  - February-March 2008, December 2008 (Box 13)
    (correspondence with Don Huggins)
  - April-June 2008 (Box 13)
  - July-August 2008 (Box 13)
  - September-November 2008 (Box 13)
  - November-December 2008 (Box 13)
  - 2009, 7 folders (Box 13)
  - 2010, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - 2010, 5 folders (Box 14)
  - 2010 (Box 14)
  - 2011, 8 folders (Box 14)
  - January 2012 (Box 14)
  - January-April 2012 (Box 14)
  - March-May 2012 (Box 14)
  - May-June 2012 (Box 14)
  - July 2012 (Box 14)
  - July-August 2012 (Box 14)
  - September-November 2012 (Box 14)
  - November 2012-February 2013 (Box 14)
  - February-April 2013 (Box 14)
  - April-July 2013 (Box 15)
  - July-August 2013 (Box 15)
  - September-October 2013 (Box 15)
    (includes brief memoir of relative's visit to Soviet Union)
  - November-December 2013 (Box 15)
    (includes letter from 1939 written by Frank Benford (father of Harry Benford) to Leonard B. Clark)
  - November 2013-March 2014 (Box 15)
  - April 2014 (Box 15)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (6 linear feet, 1937-2009) dates from 1937 to 2009 and consists of sketches, drawings, correspondence, meeting notes, project proposals, accounts, contracts, research reports, lecture notes, personnel records, departmental review memos and miscellaneous notes. The series is divided into two subseries. One subseries is arranged by year and then by topic; the other subseries of topical files is arranged alphabetically. Some of the files in this series include notes by Benford of the event or explanation of the folder's content. Included in the topically arranged subseries are photos of Benford with various groups, chiefly at meetings of the Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers
  - Arranged By Year
    - 1962
      - Proposed Research Great Lakes, 1962-1963 (Box 7)
      - Transportation Institute, 1962-1967 (Box 7)
    - 1963
      - Maritime Transportation, 1963-1967 (Box 7)
    - 1964
      - Marine Administration (MarAd) Information Center Proposal (Box 7)
    - 1966
      - South American Tour, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
    - 1967
      - Cleveland Cliffs Iron Company, Systematic Study of Transportation, 1967 (Box 7)
      - Marine Administration (MARAD) Research and Development (Box 7)
      - William Francis Gibbs Memorials, 1967-1970 (Box 7)
      - Cost Estimate Proposal (Box 7)
      - Carr Liggett Advertising Inc. (Box 7)
      - Marine Administration (MarAd) Research and Development, 1968-1969 (Box 7)
      - Education-An Investment Opportunity, 1968-1973 (Box 7)
    - 1969
      - United Front (Box 7)
      - Student Activism (papers largely concerning the policy of the University with respect to student recruitment by war-related corporations), 1969-1974 (Box 7)
    - 1970
      - University Issues, 1970-1975 (Box 7)
    - 1971
      - Model Basin (Box 7)
      - Trip to Australia and Japan, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - 1972
      - Great Lakes Shipping Cost, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
    - 1974
      - Dieter Ulken, 1974-1979 (Box 7)
      - Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers (SNAME), 1974-1975 (Box 7)
    - 1975
      - Consultant to Venezuelan Maritime Bureau (Corporacion Venezolana de la Industria Naval C.A.), 1975-1976; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers (SNAME), proposal to revise by-laws, 1975-1976 (Box 7)
    - 1976
      - Simat Panel (paper) concerning Great Lakes Overseas Transportation Market Assessment, 1976 (Box 7)
      - University of Veracruz (Box 7)
      - Phil Spaulding, Nomination for Taylor Medal, 1976-1979 (Box 7)
    - 1978 (Box 8)
      - Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers (SNAME), Spring Meeting Preparations (Box 8)
      - Scheduling Committee, University of Michigan, 1978-1979 (Box 8)
    - 1981
      - That Difficult First Step: How Cooley Brought Naval Architecture to Michigan" (a centennial article celebrating the University's history of naval architecture) (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Arranged By Topic
    - Baier, Prof. L.A. &, 1970s; 1980s (Box 8)
    - Benford, Harry, A Pictorial History of My Coal Passing Career, May 19, 2007 (Box 8)
    - Bragg, E.M., Professor. Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 8)
    - Department of NA & ME
      - Alumni Reunions, 1957-1965; 1977; 1980 (Box 8)
      - Centennial, 1981 (Box 8)
      - Departmental review memos, 1964-1980s (Box 8)
        [CLOSED: Need permission of donor]
      - Faculty/Departmental Correspondence, 1948-1983 (Box 8)
      - Papers, 1970-1981 (Box 8)
      - Papers, 1981-1985 (Box 8)
      - Proposal for new research facility, 1974 (Box 8)
    - Department of Transportation, Michigan State
      - Accounts, 1979-1981 (Box 8)
      - Contract and other legal documents, 1979 (Box 8)
      - Contract, 1979-1981 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence and Meeting notes, 1979-1980 (Box 8)
      - Economics, 1980 (Box 8)
      - Extras, 1980 (Box 8)
      - Kerkman's Trial, 1986 (Box 8)
      - Legal documents, 1979-1982 (Box 8)
      - Management Planning, Cost and Billing, 1979-1981 (Box 8)
      - McMullen Contract, 1980 (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous and Technical notes, 1980 (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous clippings, 1980-1982 (Box 8)
      - Operational Economics of ITB Rail Ferry System and Comments, 1982 (Box 8)
      - Photographs, 1980 (Box 8)
      - Reports, 1979-1981 (Box 8)
    - European Trip
      - 1983 (Box 8)
      - 1985 (Box 8)
    - Faculty Campaigns (Box 8)
    - Germany, 1977 (Box 8)
    - Glasgow, 1983 (Box 8)
    - Great Lakes Research, 1969-1976 (Box 9)
    - Hilton, Geo. Correspondence, 1990-1995 (Box 9)
    - Illies, Kurt, 1974-1978 (Box 9)
    - Japanese Attack on Pearl Harbor (Box 9)
    - Kummerman, Henri (1908-1984). Correspondence.
      - 1975-1977 (Box 9)
        (includes biographical material)
      - 1978 (Box 9)
      - 1979-1981 (Box 9)
      - 1982-1984 (Box 9)
    - Kummerman, Rene. Correspondence, 1984-1993 (Box 9)
    - Lamb, Tom, Harry Benford's Chapter in Tom Lamb's Book (Box 9)
    - Liner America, Newspaper (Box 9)
    - London Speech, 1984 (Box 9)
    - Ludwig, Daniel K., 1968-1987 (Box 9)
    - Marine Technology--Editorial Committee correspondence, 1981-1987 (Box 9)
    - Marine Transport Economics Team (MTET) (Box 9)
    - Maritime Administration (MarAd)
      - Policy, 1961-1982 (Box 9)
      - Research and Development, 1968-1970 (Box 9)
    - Maritime Policy and Management--Editorial Board correspondence, 1981-1986 (Box 9)
    - Maritime Research Advisory Committee (MARC), 1959-1960 (Box 9)
    - Master of Business Administration (MBA)/Naval Architecture, correspondence regarding combined master degree., 1980-1981 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1976 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous Organizations, 1961-1979 (Box 9)
    - Nakanishi, T., Correspondence
      - 1980-1982 (Box 10)
      - 1983-1985 (Box 10)
      - 1986 (Box 10)
      - 1990-1995 (Box 10)
      - 2000-2001 (Box 10)
    - Nautilus (newsletter)
      (Benford was editor; papers about the publication)
      - Editorship of Departmental Newsletter, 1991-1994 (Box 10)
      - Vol. 7, 1994 (Box 10)
      - Vol. 8, 1994 (Box 10)
      - Vol. 9, 1995 (Box 10)
      - Vol. 10, 1995 (Box 10)
      - Vol. 11, 1996 (Box 10)
      - Vol. 12, 1996 (Box 10)
      - Vol. 13, 1997 (Box 10)
      - Vol. 14, 1997 (Box 10)
      - Vol. 15, 1998 (Box 10)
      - Vol. 28, 2006 (Box 10)
    - Naval Architect's Guide to Practical Economics, guide, reviews, letters (Box 10)
    - Nemec's Blast, 1962-1963 (Box 10)
    - New Orleans, 1984 (Box 10)
    - Nowacki, Prof. Horst
      - 2007 (Box 10)
      - German Naval Architect (Box 10)
      - Leonhard Euler and the Theory of Ships, 2007 (Box 10)
    - Nuclear Propulsion Research, 1955 (Box 10)
    - O'Connor, Dennis, 1979 (Box 11)
    - Oral History Interview, transcript and 2 cassette tapes, 2003 (Box 11)
    - People's Republic of China (PRC). Correspondence, 1981 (Box 11)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1985 (Box 11)
    - Personnel records, 1951-1979 (Box 11)
    - Photographs (Box 11)
    - Poe Lock (proposal to increase allowable length of vessels transiting the Poe Lock), 1976 (Box 11)
    - Royal Institute of Naval Architecture, correspondence, 1962-1985 (Box 11)
    - Russian Translation of a NA's Guide to Practical Economics, 1991 (Box 11)
    - Sadler, Herbert C. presentation (Marine Safety Conference, University of Glasgow), 1983 (Box 11)
    - Schiller, sketches and reminiscence, 1937 (Box 11)
    - Sea Transport Technology (symposium and exhibition, University of New South Wales), 1981 (Box 11)
    - Seaway Review--Administrative correspondence, 1978-1987 (Box 11)
    - Ship Operations Research Committee, 1981-1984 (Box 11)
    - Shipbuilding Days, 1940-1948 (Box 11)
    - Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers (SNAME)
      - Correspondence, 1953-1977 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, 1978-1986 (Box 12)
      - Taylor Medal (won 1976); correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 12)
      - 50-Year Technical Review, 1987-1995; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Soo Locks, 1959-1964 (Box 12)
    - Technical University of Berlin
      - 1966 (Box 12)
      - Exchange with University of Michigan, 1971-1987 (Box 12)
      - 1983 (Box 12)
    - True, Dwight paper
      - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 12)
      - Sixty Years of Shipbuilding, 1956 (Box 12)
    - TV lectures, 1983-1989 (Box 12)
    - Unit Train Economics, 1971-1972 (Box 12)
    - University of Michigan Sailing Club Reunion, 2002 (Box 12)
    - Venezuela, 1975-1976 (Box 12)
    - West European Graduate Education Marine Technology (WEGEMT) summer school, 8th, 1983 (Box 12)
  - Notes from University of Michigan Faculty Women's Club, 1992-1995 (Box 13)
    (written by Betty Benford)
  - University of Michigan Quarterdeck Society Newsletter, 2007 (Box 13)
  - Presentation on Riveted Ships to Great Lakes and Great Rivers Section of Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers, 2009 (Box 13)